

# **Bernardo Di Chiara**

## Data Analyst

dichiarabernardo@gmail.com

Passionate about Statistics and Data Analysis. Able to handle huge amount of data.

20 years' experience in dealing with customer requirements, recent computer programming experience. Strong logical and analytical skills, critical thinker with attention to details, excellent documentation skills.

#### **Professional Skills**

- Data Analysis Techniques (Data Dumping, Data Cleansing, Data Preparation, Data Visualization), Machine Learning (Classification & Regression)
- Statistics (Exploratory Data Analysis, Inferential Data Analysis)
- Databases: SQL, Hadoop, MapReduce, Spark
- Computer programming (SW development)
- Requirement Management
- Product/Feature/System Specifications
- Acceptance Test Cases Definition
- Best Practices' Development, Agile approach
- Coaching and Consulting, Leading Functional Teams
- Product Management

## **Personal Skills**

- Self-steering
- Critical thinking
- Analytic approach
- Precise

#### **Professional Achievements**

- Being used several times as a model when developing internal practices related to requirement analysis
- Being acknowledged several times by colleagues for having added quality to internal and external product documentation
- Having received very good feedback (5,6/6) from the attendants to competence transfer sessions
- Having affected the decision of major customers to buy our solution
- Being ranked as Exceptional in the Yearly Performance Evaluation several times
- Receiving Achievement Award from the Product Line for the outstanding job

## Language Skills

- Italian (native language)
- English (fluently)
- Finnish (good knowledge)

#### Computer Skills

- Operating systems: Windows 10 and previous versions, Linux, Android
- Languages: Python (including Pandas, Matplotlib and Sklearn), R, SQL, HTML
- Cloud computing: Amazon Web Services
- Data analysis SW (MySQL Workbench, Jupyter Notebook, RStudio, Power BI, KNIME, RapidMiner)
- Web frameworks (Django, Flask); Containers (Docker); Security (Bitvise SSH Client); CADs (MS Visio);
   Concurrent SW projects (GitLab, Wiki); Common Office Apps (Word, PowerPoint, Excel, Outlook, Thunderbird)

## References



"Bernardo is a hard-working and task-oriented selfstarter. He has a track record of delivering results

in time and with high quality" Antti
Pikkusaari, Management Consultant at
Aedon Oy & at Taival



"He's a great team player" Timo Leppäkorpi, Testing Coordinator at Apotti



"Very seldom I have seen such a WoW factor when it comes to the performance of an

individual. His skills in data engineering are impressive, including excellent technical knowhow in Python, MySQL, AWS, and other modern technologies." Esa Vepsäläinen, CTO, Optiwatti



"A combination of customer understanding, technical expertise and co-operation skills makes Bernardo very

valuable and pleasant to work with" Tuija Hurtta, Product Manager at Nokia



"He is able to understand and analyze wide and complex topics" Seppo Huotari, Manager at Nokia CV: Bernardo Di Chiara Page 2

#### **Work History**

Current Position

## System Developer

**Optiwatti** 

 Handling big databases with hundreds of gigabytes and being responsible of data engineering tasks as databases' re-organization and data migration

- Exploratory Data Analysis (pandas, matplotlib)
- SW development: requirements' collection, SW design, coding, testing, documentation (MySQL, Python, Django framework, Amazon Web Services, Linux)

May 2017 - Nov 2018

#### Improving my Data Analytics Skills

(see my portfolio)

- Data Retrieval, Data Cleansing, Data Preparation, Data Visualization
- Programming in R and Python, Supervised and Unsupervised Machine Learning
- Statistics: Exploratory & Inferential Data Analysis
- Databases: SQL, Hadoop, MapReduce, Spark
- User Experience Research Methods

Jan 2010 - Dec 2016

## Senior System Architect

Nokia

- Leading functional teams and being responsible of creating and maintaining several feasibility studies and requirement specifications by using Agile approach
- Defining acceptance test scenarios together with test engineers
- Maintaining Statements of Compliance for several features and interfaces
- Supervising Master Thesis works (coaching)

May 2009 - Dec 2009

Product Planning Manager

Sabbatical

**Nokia Siemens Networks** 

- Defining the content of a new product by coordinating the work of a group of people and by actively participating in the specification
- Defining best practices and customizing a new requirement handling tool
- Facilitating the maintenance of the Road Map of different products

Mar 2004 - Mar 2007

#### Senior Solution Manager

**Nokia Networks** 

- Providing consulting work and designing customized solutions with major global customers by specifying new features and integrating with third party products
- Running internal competence transfer sessions to Marketing and to Engineers

Mar 2003 - Feb 2004

#### **Network Architect**

**Nokia Networks** 

 Being responsible for the specification of key functionality in system releases composed of several products (defining and documenting the requirements)

Apr 2000- Feb 2003

#### System Product Manager

Nokia Networks

- Collecting requirements from customers and giving input to Development regarding several end-to-end functionalities
- Creating and maintaining contacts with other Business Units in order to coordinate release contents and schedules and in order to support marketing activities
- Creating communication slide sets for internal and external purposes
- Contributing to the creation of product related marketing material (including Road Maps, Product Descriptions and Feature Descriptions)

Nov 1997 - Mar 2000

## Senior System Engineer

Nokia Networks

- Being responsible of several front end and back end requirement specification projects (requirement specifications, feasibility studies, implementation specific.)
- Participating in Standardization as a Nokia Main Delegate in 3GPP forum

CV: Bernardo Di Chiara Page 3

#### Education

• Master of Science in Electric Engineering (110/110 with honor), Palermo's University, Italy

 General Certificate of Education from High School specializing in scientific studies, School Don Bosco Villa Ranchibile, Palermo, Italy

• Data Analytics Courses (about 1000 hours of study, see more in my development plan). An excerpt:

Topic	Course	Grade	Ву	Completion Date
Statistics	Inferential Statistics (in R)	100%	Duke University on	Nov 28 <sup>th</sup> 2017
	Linear Regression and Modeling (in R)	100%	Coursera	Mar 14 <sup>th</sup> 2018
	Introduction to Probability and Data	98,7%		Oct 17 <sup>th</sup> 2017
	(exploratory data analysis in R)			
R	R Programming	100%	Johns Hopkins University on Coursera	Jan 16 <sup>th</sup> 2018
	Practical Machine Learning (in R)	100%		Apr 13 <sup>th</sup> 2018
	Getting and Cleaning Data (in R)	100%		Feb 19 <sup>th</sup> 2018
Python	Applied Plotting, Charting and Data	100%	University of Michigan on Coursera	Nov 6 <sup>th</sup> 2018
	Representation in Python			
	Introduction to Data Science in Python	100%		Oct 9 <sup>th</sup> 2018
	(data cleansing and manipulation)			
	Using Databases with Python	98%		Nov 29 <sup>th</sup> 2018
	Using Python to Access Web Data	100%		Nov 19 <sup>th</sup> 2018
	Python Data Structures	100%		Sep 11 <sup>th</sup> 2018
	Getting Started with Python	100%		Sep 5 <sup>th</sup> 2018
Databases	SQL for Data Science	100%	Univ. of California Davis	May 19 <sup>th</sup> 2018
	Hadoop Platform and Application	100%	Univ. of California, San	Jun 29 <sup>th</sup> 2018
	Framework		Diego on Coursera	

- Self-Management, Leadership and Selling Courses
  - Boosting Your Leadership Skills (grade: A-) (by Aalto University, Oct 8<sup>th</sup> 2016)
  - o Entrepreneurship training (by Nestholma, *Jun 21*<sup>st</sup> *2016*)
  - o Focused Mind (Web based course, 2012)
  - Creative Thinking (Web based course, 2003)
  - o Presentation Skills (by Delta Training, 1996)
  - o Cross Cultural Awareness (by Richard Lewis Communications, 1996)
  - o Funnel Effective Sales Negotiation (by Jorma Kylander Oy, 1996)
- Quite few technical courses in the **telecom** / datacom field (1997 2016)

#### Other Interests

- Sailing
  - Forming and managing crews as a skipper is an excellent way to maintain team building and leadership skills. Running the boat allows nurturing goal setting and planning skills
- Boat maintenance and reparation work
  - An efficient way to improve problem solving capabilities
- Psychology (a lot of self-reading, including Freud, Goleman, Atkinson & Hilgard's, ...)
  - o Increases self-awareness and improves communication skills
- Playing keyboards and ukulele
  - An excellent exercise for both the hemispheres of the brain
- Swimming
  - o Healthy mind in a healthy body

#### Where to Find More

in http://fi.linkedin.com/in/bernardodichiara

GitHub <a href="https://github.com/BerniHacker/CV/blob/master/README.md">https://github.com/BerniHacker/CV/blob/master/README.md</a> (portfolio and development plan)